Guide to the Hines 50th Anniversary Exhibition Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Hines 50th Anniversary Exhibition Collection
2007
01/2015-018
American Institute of Architects. Houston Chapter
61.00 items
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection consists of 59 exhibition panels, two large light boxes with transparencies, and mounting hardware. The exhibition purports to show fifty Hines projects, but the materials received from the donor include only 48.
Historical Note:
AIA Houston is the local chapter of the American Institute of Architects. AIA Houston is a community of architects coming together to accomplish things in our practices and in our communities that no single architect can do alone.
AIA Houston Goals: Include others as we strive to enhance professional excellence and quality of life in Houston; connect our industry and our community through the development of leadership and research; support member value with a nimble and innovative chapter organization.
Sources:
https://aiahouston.org/v/about/
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Exhibition records; Photographs
Topical Term:
Architecture; Commercial real estate; Real Estate Developers
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 59 exhibition panels, two large light boxes with transparencies, and mounting hardware. The exhibition purports to show fifty Hines projects, but the materials received from the donor include only 48.
In 2007 the American Institute of Architects, Houston Chapter celebrated the fiftieth anniversary of the Hines Company with an exhibition entitled, “HINES / 50 YEARS / 50 SELECTED WORKS.” The exhibition appeared at the AIA Houston offices and at the gallery of the Williams Tower in Houston. The large text panel describes the content of the exhibition as follows:
HINES / 50 YEARS / 50 SELECTED WORKS
Ultimately, the remarkable legacy of Hines will be measured in the powerful and profound architecture it has constructed throughout the world. Gerald D. Hines is known for his singular ability to do the right thing at the right time. His vision and architectural sensibility have consistently driven decisions since 1957 when he hired Neuhaus & Taylor, a premier Houston architectural firm, to design his first small development. The measured growth of Hines from a one-man show to an international operation of 3,350 employees began with the transformation of the Richmond Avenue Corridor. Expanding into downtown Houston, Hines remade the city’s skyline engendering national recognition that remade the city’s reputation as well. From Houston, Hines reached into other large U.S. cities with projects that, like the Houston buildings, attracted attention for extraordinary design, innovative construction, and workable space. By the 1990s international projects, first in Mexico and Europe then Asia, rivaled those in the U.S. in terms of size and architectural significance.
The 50 projects in this exhibition were carefully chosen to show chronological, geographic, and architectural diversity. Each represents many others that could have been included. Architectural firms headquartered in Houston – Neuhaus & Taylor, Wilson, Morris Crain & Anderson (now Morris Architects), and Kendall/Heaton Associates stand alongside nationally known architects such as Cesar Pelli, Frank Gehry, Philip Johnson, Kevin Roche, David Childs, Bruce Graham, Eugene Kohn, Mario Cucinella, Norman Foster, I.M. Pei, Harry Cobb, Robert A.M. Stern, and many others. Hines buildings are never formulaic, and even those designed by the same architect are distinctive. The variety of building types, spaces, places and architecture that Hines continues to develop brings richness to an oeuvre that will engage and fascinate generations to come.
THIS EXHIBITION IS SPONSORED BY
AIA Houston – Aker Zvonkovic Photography – Baker & Botts, LLP – Harvey Builders – Haynes Whaley Associates – HILL – Kendall/Heaton Associates
Detailed List of Contents
- Exhibit Panels
  - Willowick Apartments (1963), Houston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 1)
  - 3000 Richmond (1963), Houston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 2)
  - The Galleria (1970), Houston, 2 panels, 2007 (Item 3)
  - One Shell Plaza (1971), Houston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 4)
  - Pennzoil Place (1975), Houston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 5)
  - Post Oak Central (One, Two and Three) (1975-1982), Houston, 2 panels, 2007 (Item 6)
  - 1100 Louisiana (1980), Houston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 7)
  - U.S. Bank Plaza (Pillsbury Center) (1981), Minneapolis, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 8)
  - J P Morgan Chase (Texas Commerce Bank) (1982), Houston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 9)
  - 101 California (1982), San Francisco, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 10)
  - Wells Fargo Center (One Norwest Center) (1983), Denver, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 11)
  - Bank of America (RepublicBank) Center (1983), Houston, 3 panels, 2007 (Item 12)
  - Huntington Center (1984), Columbus OH, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 13)
  - Wachovia Financial Center (1984), Miami, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 14)
  - 580 California (1984), San Francisco, 2 panels, 2007 (Item 15)
  - Ravinia (1985-1991), Atlanta, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 16)
  - 53rd at 3rd Avenue (“Lipstick Bldg.”) (1986), NYC, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 17)
  - Wells Fargo Northwest (Norwest Center) (1987), Minneapolis, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 18)
  - 500 Boylston (1988), Boston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 19)
  - Figueroa at Wilshire (1990), Los Angeles, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 20)
  - 191 Peachtree Tower (1991), Atlanta, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 21)
  - Comerica Tower (1991), Detroit, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 22)
  - St. Luke’s Professional Bldg. (1991), Houston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 23)
  - Owens Corning World Headquarters (1996), Toledo, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 24)
  - Del Bosque (1997), Mexico City, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 25)
  - DZ Bank (1999), Berlin, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 26)
  - Torre del Angel (2000), Mexico City, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 27)
  - Gannett/USA Today (2001), McLean, VA, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 28)
  - 745 Seventh Avenue (2001), NYC, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 29)
  - EDF Tower (2001), Paris, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 30)
  - 383 Madison Avenue (2002), NYC, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 31)
  - 191 North Wacker Drive (2002), Chicago, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 32)
  - Embassy House (2002), Beijing, China, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 33)
  - 1500 Louisiana (2002), Houston, 3 panels, 2007 (Item 34)
  - 540 West Madison (2003), Chicago, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 35)
  - Ben Rather Karree (2003), Dusseldorf, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 36)
  - Calpine Bldg. (2003), Houston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 37)
  - Metropolitan (2003), Warsaw, Poland, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 38)
  - 99 Queen Victoria Street (2004), London, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 39)
  - Uptown Munchen (2004), Munich, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 40)
  - Torre Almirante (2004), Rio de Janeiro, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 41)
  - Union Pacific Center (2004), Omaha, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 42)
  - One South Dearborn (2005), Chicago, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 43)
  - Portico (2005), Madrid, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 44)
  - 1180 Peachtree (2006), Atlanta, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 45)
  - Diagonal Mar Development (2006), Barcelona, Spain, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 46)
  - Ducat Place III (2006), Moscow, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 47)
  - Meudon Campus (2007), Meudon, France, 1 panel (Item 48)
  - Aerial photo, IH 610 West Loop area, showing Hines development sites, Houston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 49)
  - Aerial photo, downtown Houston, showing Hines development sites, Houston, 1 panel, 2007 (Item 50)
  - Text boards, 2 panels, 2007 (Item 51)
  - Two light boxes with transparencies of the Houston Galleria and downtown Houston, 2007 (Item 52)